<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://dscience7.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://dscience7.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-04-10T16:16:04+01:00</updated><id>https://dscience7.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Amjad Karim</title><subtitle>Personal Blog</subtitle><author><name>Amjad Karim</name></author><entry><title type="html">An Immortal Coat Hanger</title><link href="https://dscience7.github.io/2023-04-10/An-Immortal-Coat-Hanger" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Immortal Coat Hanger" /><published>2023-04-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-04-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://dscience7.github.io/2023-04-10/An%20Immortal%20Coat%20Hanger</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dscience7.github.io/2023-04-10/An-Immortal-Coat-Hanger"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/hanger.png" alt="an immortal hanger" /></p>

<p>Sci-fi writers and some technologists propose that one day we will achieve immortality by uploading ourselves to a computer and living in cyberspace. The idea is our concious mind is a pattern and it can be copied from a biological substrate to a digital one. I’ve always worried this won’t give you immortality but at best another conscious being that thinks it’s you and at worst its suicide. The original biological you would remain where it started i.e. in your body. So either you die and a copy of you carries on or there are two distinct versions of you. The original you wouldn’t achieve immortality but something else does.</p>

<p>We can use the ideas contained in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ship_of_Theseus">Ship of Theseus</a> paradox to create a scheme for transferring a conciousness from a mortal body to an immortal one (or at least one we know how to infinitely repair).</p>

<h2 id="the-ship-of-theseus">The Ship of Theseus</h2>
<p>The Ship of Theseus is an ancient thought experiment about whether an object where all of it’s component parts have been replaced remains the same object.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The ship wherein Theseus and the youth of Athens returned from Crete had thirty oars, and was preserved by the Athenians down even to the time of Demetrius Phalereus, for they took away the old planks as they decayed, putting in new and stronger timber in their places, insomuch that this ship became a standing example among the philosophers, for the logical question of things that grow; one side holding that the ship remained the same, and the other contending that it was not the same.
    — Plutarch, Life of Theseus 23.1</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="an-immortal-coat-hanger">An Immortal Coat Hanger</h2>
<p>Before we tackle something as complex as a brain, let’s start with something much simpler, a hanger holding up a pair of trousers in a wardrobe. The idea is to replace every part of the coat hanger without ever becoming unhooked or the trousers coming off the hanger. Our imaginary coat hanger is connected to rail inside a wardrobe by a metal hook, the trousers rest on the hanger across a triangular piece of wood. How can we replace the hook without the hanger falling down? If we try and replace the hook in one go then we’ll be forced to separate the original hook from wooden part of the hanger and so there comes a time when the trousers are no longer hooked to the rail in the wardrobe. What if took a chunk of the hook and try to swap it out? If the chunk is too big then we’ll split the hook into two pieces, but, if we zoomed in further we could update the hook atom by atom. Removing a single atom doesn’t “break” the hook and the atom can be replaced by another one. We carry on this fashion until the entire object is the same but no longer the same.</p>

<h2 id="an-immortal-mind">An Immortal Mind</h2>
<p>Similarly, rather than upload your entire mind to another system in one go, we replace individual biological components one at a time with artificial ones which have the exact same function but have the bonus of being infinitely repairable. So for a brain we’d swap out one biological neuron with an artificial one modelled on it. The artificial neuron behaves exactly as the biological one and is connected to all the neurons the original biological neuron was connected to. After the operation is finished you’d wake up and wouldn’t notice a difference. We repeat this exercise for each neuron in turn. Eventually your biological brain has been swapped entirely and is now artificial. Your sense of self is continuous and there is still only one of you and you haven’t committed suicide. Obviously, the brain is made up of more than just neurons so we’d need to replace these other things to but it shouldn’t stop our scheme from working.</p>

<h2 id="materialism-dualism-and-panpsychism">Materialism, Dualism and Panpsychism</h2>
<p>For this to work the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Materialism">Materialist</a> view on conciousness would need to be correct. Materialism posits matter is the fundamental substance in nature and conciousness arises from the way matter is organised. It wouldn’t work if <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mind%E2%80%93body_dualism">Dualism</a> is correct, the idea that mind and body are separate but interact in someway. It may work under <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panpsychism">Panpsychism</a>. Panpsychists believe consciousness is a fundamental property of matter such as mass and that everything in the universe has some element of consciousness no matter how small. Certain arrangements of matter combine to form more significant forms of consciousness. Our thought experiment could work in a panpsychist universe but we may need to figure out how to arrange matter correctly to form the correct consciousness.</p>]]></content><author><name>Amjad Karim</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>